Guide to the Patriotic Envelope Collection [1861-1865], 1898 PR 117
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
Patriotic Envelope Collection
[1861-1865], 1898
PR 117
© 2011 New-York Historical Society
2.6 Linear feet (9 boxes)
Patriotic printed envelopes, dating from the Civil War and the Spanish American War. Civil War examples include both Union and Confederate envelopes, with several hundred by New York printer Charles Magnus.
Provenance
Various donors.
Access Restrictions
Open to qualified researchers.
Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to 30 photocopies per day per person. Suitability of the original for photocopying is at the discretion of the staff. Neither blueprints nor tracings can be copied under any circumstances. Duplication of large-format items will be done by the house photographer. See Print Room guidelines for details.
Historical Note
The printed envelope came into use in America in 1840 and was first used for advertising or satirical purposes. In the 1850s to 1860s 'corner cards,' with printing applied in the upper left-hand side of the front of the envelope, were common. By the onset of the Civil War, printed envelopes were already in use as a propaganda medium. Lithography was the main mode of printing used for envelopes, especially for colored designs. Printed envelopes were sold either as a single item or with matching paper.
New York City was considered the printing capital of the United States from about 1825 and continued to be so during the Civil War years. Despite New York's official status as a Union state, many residents of New York City were not so assuredly in favor of the Union, or even of the war itself. In 1863 the city saw riots in Union Square and elsewhere protesting the draft and other war hardships. Such commotion in the nation's biggest city may have added more weight to the need for distribution of pro-Union propaganda. Printed envelopes continued to be popular throughout the century, and patriotic envelopes were printed once again during the Spanish American War in 1898.
Many envelopes in the Civil War series were printed by Charles Magnus, a prominent New York City lithographer. Magnus came to the United States from Germany following the political upheavals in Europe in 1848. He was an accomplished lithographer, and developed a following of customers who purchased his many printed products - maps, games, lettersheets, and artistic prints as well as political envelopes.
Scope and Content Note
The Patriotic Envelope Collection spans the period from 1861 to 1898, with the vast majority dated between 1861 and 1865, and contains approximately 3,000 envelopes with patriotic scenes and text printed on their exterior. It is arranged into two series: I. Civil War Envelopes and II. Spanish American War Envelopes. Most envelopes measure approximately 3 x 5 1/2 inches. The Collection was removed from the Graphic Arts File during processing.
The envelopes are printed or embossed with caricatures, allegories, slogans, and portraits relating to war events and personalities. The vast majority are Union-oriented from the Civil War; most were produced by New York printers. Some are quite crude; others are beautifully designed and executed, many are in color, with some even printed in gilt. Scenes or text appears on most of the envelopes in the upper left hand corner. Sometimes the printing extends across the upper front of the envelope, or to the verso. Several envelopes contain duplicates of the same image, often in different colored ink.
Oversize material includes a few pictorial lettersheets from each war, as well as oversize (often legal-sized) envelopes.
A representation of 490 Civil War envelopes, selected to represent the breadth of the collection, were scanned as part of the Mellon Digital Project and can be viewed on the Library of Congress' American Memory website at the following url: "http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/ndlpcoop/nhihtml/cwnyhsarc.html." These envelopes can also be searched through the Print Room Collections Database.
Arrangement
Within series, the collection is organized alphabetically by subject.
Listed subjects for Civil War envelopes are: African-Americans, American eagle, animals, U.S. Constitution, death, flags, foreign affairs, Fort Sumter, Liberty/Columbia, monuments, Satan, ships, soldiers and sailors, states (further divided by Union, Border, and Confederate), portraits (arranged alphabetically), U.S. shield, U.S. star, Unlce Sam, women, Zouaves, and miscellaneous images (further divided by Union, secession and Confederate scenes). Envelopes printed by Charles Magnus are kept together, and are further divided by American eagles, camp scenes, soldiers and sailors, cities, states, portraits and the Star Spangled Banner. A few oversize envelopes include images of camp scenes and flags.
Spanish American War envelopes are organized by portrait and then by subject.
The Collection is divided into two series:
Series I. Civil War Envelopes
Series II. Spanish American War Envelopes
Related Material at The New-York Historical Society
Many collections at the Department of Prints, Photographs, and Architectural Collections include Civil War-era material. These include the Stereograph File (PR 055), the Poster File (PR 055), the Album File (PR 002), the Caricature and Cartoon File (PR 010), the Portrait File (PR 052), War of the Rebellion Albums (PR 088), the Subject File (PR 068), and the Matthew Brady Studio Collection (PR 085). In 2000, many of the holdings from these collections were digitized and can be viewed as part of the Library of Congress' American Memory project, at "http://memory.loc.gov/ammem/ndlpcoop/nhihtml/cwnyhsarc.html." In addition, the Bella C. Landauer Collection of Business and Advertising Ephemera (PR 031) contains many further examples of printed stationery and other ephemera.
Spanish American War material can be found in the Album File (PR 002), Robert L. Bracklow Photograph Collection (PR 008), Burr McIntosh Photograph Collection (PR 041), the Portrait File (PR 052), the Poster File (PR 055), the Stereograph File (PR 065), the Subject File (PR 068), and the Playing Card and Game Collection (PR 115).
The New-York Historical Library and the Manuscripts Department also hold many Civil War and Spanish American War collections.
Beauregard, G. T. (Gustave Toutant), 1818-1893--Portraits; Butler, Benjamin F. (Benjamin Franklin), 1818-1893--Portraits; Davis, Jefferson, 1808-1889--Caricatures and cartoons; Dewey, George, 1837-1917--Portraits; Franklin, Benjamin, 1706-1790--Portraits; Lee, Fitzhugh, 1835-1905--Portraits; Lincoln, Abraham, 1809-1865--Portraits; Magnus, Charles, printer; McKinley, William, 1843-1901–Portraits; Roosevelt, Theodore, 1858-1919-- Portraits; Sampson, William Thomas, 1840-1902--Portraits; Schley, Winfield Scott, 1839-1909--Portraits; Scott, Winfield, 1786-1866--Caricatures and cartoons; Shafter, William Rufus, 1835-1906--Portraits; Washington, George, 1732-1799--Portraits; Caricatures; Caricatures and cartoons–United States; Envelopes; Envelopes (Stationery); Ephemera; Political Cartoons; Political cartoons–United States; Stationery; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865--Caricatures and cartoons; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865–Participation, African American; United States--History--Civil War, 1861-1865–Propaganda
- Series I: Civil War Envelopes
  Scope and Contents note
  Series I contains approximately 2900 envelopes, which are organized alphabetically by subject. Many envelopes show portraits or caricatures of contemporary politicians such as Jefferson Davis and Abraham Lincoln, as well as patriotic figures George Washington and Benjamin Franklin. Generals (such as Beauregard, Scott, and Butler) and other Civil War figures also appear. State seals figure prominently, as do flags. Other significant topics in the collection are animals (especially the American eagle), Liberty, soldiers, sailors, Uncle Sam, and depictions of women and African Americans. Between two and three hundred envelopes (all of which are in Box 3) were printed by Charles Magnus. Several Magnus envelopes show Civil War camp scenes derived from photographs. These envelopes show detailed scenes of soldiers relaxing in camp, standing guard, and cleaning their guns. Each of these envelopes contains the printed phrase "From Photograph" under the scene.
  Box 9 contains an unbound scrapbook (housed in 13 folders) titled "Letter-envelopes current in 1861," printed in Baltimore. The provenance of this item is unclear, but a few handwritten comments by the original owner can be found. Several envelopes are pasted on each page, often organized by design or subject. This could be a useful reference for determining which other envelopes in the collection may have been printed in 1861.
  - African-Americans, [1861-1865] (Box 1)
  - American eagle--miscellaneous, [1861-1865] (Box 1)
    General note
    See also Box 3
  - American eagle--with flag, [1861-1865] (Box 1)
  - American eagle--with shield, [1861-1865] (Box 1)
  - American eagle--with flag and shield, [1861-1865] (Box 1)
  - American eagle--with globe, [1861-1865] (Box 1)
  - American eagle--with serpent, [1861-1865] (Box 1)
  - Animals--miscellaneous, [1861-1865] (Box 1)
  - Animals--Generals Winfield Scott/Jefferson Davis as dogs, [1861-1865] (Box 1)
  - Constitution (U.S.), [1861-1865] (Box 2)
  - Death's head, [1861-1865] (Box 2)
  - Flags--Union, [1861-1865] (Box 2)
    See also Box 8
  - Flags--Confederate, [1861-1865] (Box 2)
  - Foreign affairs, [1861-1865] (Box 2)
  - Fort Sumter, [1861-1865] (Box 2)
  - Liberty/Columbia, [1861-1865] (Box 2)
  - Magnus, Charles, Printer (works attributed to)-Miscellaneous, [1861-1865] (Box 3)
  - Magnus, Charles, Printer (works attributed to) -- American eagles, [1861-1865] (Box 3)
    See also Box 1
  - Magnus, Charles, Printer (works attributed to)--Camp scenes, [1861-1865] (Box 3)
  - Magnus, Charles, Printer (works attributed to)--Soldiers and sailors, [1861-1865] (Box 3)
    See also Box 4
  - Magnus, Charles, Printer (works attributed to)--Cities, Miscellaneous, [1861-1865] (Box 3)
  - Magnus, Charles, Printer (works attributed to)--Cities--Washington, D.C., [1861-1865] (Box 3)
  - Magnus, Charles, Printer (works attributed to)--States, [1861-1865] (Box 3)
  - Magnus, Charles, Printer (works attributed to)--Portraits, [1861-1865] (Box 3)
    See also Boxes 5 and 6
  - Magnus, Charles, Printer (works attributed to)--Star Spangled Banner, [1861-1865] (Box 3)
  - Monuments, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - Satan, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - Ships, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Union--Connecticut, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Union--Delaware, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Union--Illinois, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Union--Indiana, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Union--Iowa, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Union--Kansas, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Union--Maine, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Union--Massachusetts, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Union--Michigan, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Union--Minnesota, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Union--Nebraska, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Union--New Hampshire, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Union--New Jersey, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Union--New York, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Union--Ohio, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Union--Oregon, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Union--Pennsylvania, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Union--Rhode Island, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Union--Utah, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Union--Vermont, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Union--Wisconsin, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Border States--Kentucky, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Border States--Maryland, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Border States--Missouri, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Confederate--Alabama, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Confederate--Arkansas, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Confederate--Florida, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Confederate--Georgia, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Confederate--Louisiana, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Confederate--Mississippi, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Confederate--North Carolina, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Confederate--South Carolina, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Confederate--Tennessee, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Confederate--Texas, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - States--Confederate--Virginia, [1861-1865] (Box 4)
  - Portraits--A -- B miscellaneous, [1861-1865] (Box 5)
  - Portraits--Beauregard, Pierre Gustave Toutant de, [1861-1865] (Box 5)
  - Portraits--Butler, Benjamin Franklin, [1861-1865] (Box 5)
  - Portraits--C -- D miscellaneous, [1861-1865] (Box 5)
  - Portraits--Davis, Jefferson, [1861-1865] (Box 5)
  - Portraits--Douglas, Stephen Arnold, [1861-1865] (Box 5)
  - Portraits--E -- F miscellaneous, [1861-1865] (Box 5)
  - Portraits--Ellsworth, Elmer Ephraim, [1861-1865] (Box 5)
  - Portraits--Franklin, Benjamin, [1861-1865] (Box 5)
  - Portraits--Fremont, John Charles, [1861-1865] (Box 5)
  - Portraits--G -- K miscellaneous, [1861-1865] (Box 6)
  - Portraits--L -- R miscellaneous, [1861-1865] (Box 6)
  - Portraits--Lincoln, Abraham, [1861-1865] (Box 6)
  - Portraits--McClellan, George Brinton, [1861-1865] (Box 6)
  - Portraits--S -- Z miscellaneous, [1861-1865] (Box 6)
  - Portraits--Scott, Winfield, [1861-1865] (Box 6)
  - Portraits--Washington, George--Bust-length, [1861-1865] (Box 6)
  - Portraits--Washington, George--Full-length, [1861-1865] (Box 6)
  - Portraits--Washington, George--Equestrian, [1861-1865] (Box 6)
  - Portraits--Washington, Martha, [1861-1865] (Box 6)
  - United States Shield, [1861-1865] (Box 7)
  - United States Star, [1861-1865] (Box 7)
  - Uncle Sam, [1861-1865] (Box 7)
  - Women, [1861-1865] (Box 7)
  - Zouaves, [1861-1865] (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous Union Images, [1861-1865] (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous Secession Images, [1861-1865] (Box 7)
  - Miscellaneous Pro-Confederate Images, [1861-1865] (Box 7)
- Series II: Spanish American War Envelopes
  Series II contains approximately 100 envelopes and pictorial lettersheets. Envelopes are organized by portrait and by subject. Important political and war figures shown are: Colonel Roosevelt, Commodores Watson and Schley, Admirals Dewey and Sampson, General Shafter, President McKinley, and the American consul-general to Cuba, Fitzhugh Lee. The U.S.S. Maine is memorialized on envelopes and lettersheets.
  - Portraits, [1898] (Box 7)
    See also: Box 8
  - Subjects, [1898] (Box 7)
- Oversize Material
  - Civil War Envelopes, [1861-1865] (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - Civil War pictorial lettersheets, [1861-1865] (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Civil War ephemera, [1861-1865] (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Spanish American War envelopes, [1898] (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Spanish American War pictorial lettersheets, [1898] (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Civil War unbound envelope scrapbook, 1861 (Box 9)